<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<chapter id="chapter_1">

  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <sect1 id="chapter_1-sect-1">
    <para>Computer software is getting more and more complex. Software 
    projects of today, while equal in actual scope, are far more ambitious
    in their goals than those of the IBM OS/360 project to which Frederick 
    Brooks relates in his seminal work 
    "The Mythical Man-Month"<xref linkend="brooks-1975"/>. While software 
    engineering as a field is better understood now than it was in the
    mid-sixties, you will find few researchers in the field claiming that this
    understanding has kept up with the growth in the complexity of software 
    projects.</para>
    
    <para>In fact, in a world where Visual Basic is one of the most popular
    programming languages, one can easily argue that the developer pool has a 
    larger portion of relatively unskilled programmers now than ever. Yet, 
    some of the software even from this segment has complexity requirements
    that would leave the Fred Brooks anno 1965 dumbfounded. And while not all
    of this software will stand as shiny examples of software engineering, 
    it is hard to deny the fact that software written by unskilled 
    developers plays an important part in our society. </para>
    
    <para>While software engineering hasn't quite been able to meet
    the expectations once held for it (one constantly sees figures of up
    to 80% failure in software projects TODO), it is obvious that something
    has enabled programmers to build more and more complex software. And if
    this "something" isn't a vastly increased understanding of the art and 
    science of software engineering, what is it?</para>
    
    <para>The answer is simple: the tools and languages we use today
    are orders of magnitude better than what the developers under Brooks
    had available. OS/360 was written wholly in assembly code, which was
    (and still is) hard to write and debug, mainly because of its lack of
    abstraction and its conceptual distance from the problem domain.</para>
    
    <para>In contrast, we have today at our disposal a vast array
    of very high level languages. Languages like Visual Basic, Python, Java
    and C# maintain a high level of abstraction from the actual hardware, and
    often come with massive standard libraries that enables the developer
    to focus on the core functionality of his application, rather than 
    constantly having to reinvent the wheel. 
    </para>
    
    <para>While the availability of high quality standard libraries go a long
    way in explaining the increased productivity of todays' developers, it is 
    hardly the only reason. One other feature the aforementioned languages all
    have in common is that they free the developer from the responsibility of
    manually managing memory. Memory related bugs are all too common in
    traditional lower-level languages (who has never accessed a pointer whose
    backing memory has been freed<footnote><para>This is commonly referred
    to as a "dangling" pointer.</para></footnote>?), and tracking down these
    bugs can take up an inordinate amount of developer time, especially in more
    complex software. The newer languages basically makes this a non-issue by
    handling the allocation and de-allocation of memory in the language
    runtime, thus relieving the developer of this rather tedious burden.</para> 
    
    <para>And while hard core C/C++ developers still maintain, in some kind of 
     misunderstood machismo, that memory management "is too important to be 
     left to the computer"<footnote><para>It is a long-standing joke:
     C programmers have long understood that memory management is so critical
     it can't be left up to the system, and Lisp programmers have long understood
     that memory management is so critical, it can't be left up to the 
     programmers. TODO-source</para></footnote> it is becoming more and more
     clear that automatic memory management, in various implementations, is
     here to stay. The past couple of years have seen a steady shift towards
     the use of higher level programming languages and tools for all but the 
     most low-level of development tasks (operating systems, drivers, 3D graphics 
     engines etc.) And the higher level languages all invariably support 
     automatic memory management.</para>       
  </sect1>    
  
</chapter>
