<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<chapter id="chapter_3">
  <title>The Shared Source CLI (Rotor)</title>
  
  <sect1 id="chapter_3-sect-1">
    <title>ECMA 335</title>
    <para>In August 2000, while developing their new architecture known as .NET,
    Microsoft decided to submit the specification of the runtime engine and
    the new C# language to the European Computer Manufacturers' Association. These
    two elements of .NET were ratified by ECMA as ECMA standards 334
    <xref linkend="ecma-334"/> and 335<xref linkend="ecma-335"/> in December 2001;
    ECMA-334 describing the C# language and ECMA-335 describing the execution 
    environment.</para>
    <para>From the preface to ECMA-335:</para>
    
    <blockquote>
      This Standard ECMA-335 defines the Common Language Infrastructure (CLI) 
      in which applications written in multiple high level languages may be 
      executed in different system environments without the need to rewrite 
      the application to take into consideration the unique characteristics 
      of those environments.
    </blockquote>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="chapter_3-sect-2">
    <title>Rotor</title>
    <para>The Shared Source Common Language Infrastructure, or 
    <firstterm>Rotor</firstterm>, is an implementation of ECMA 335 and 
    ECMA-335 in source form, released by Microsoft in 2002. Rotor contains 
    source code for a large set of libraries, tools and compilers, including
    the JIT compiler and the virtual machine.</para>
    
    <para>The source code for Rotor was derived from 
    Microsoft's commercial implementation of .NET, but forked and modified to 
    build and run on the Mac OS X and FreeBSD operating systems in addition to 
    Microsoft Windows. It is also easily portable to other operating systems
    and CPU architectures (it currently supports IA/32 and PowerPC CPUs). It 
    comes with a full implementation of the Base Class Library (BCL), but
    libraries outside the scope of the standard such as the ASP.NET web
    framework and the Windows Forms GUI toolkit are not included.</para> 
    
    <para>This text will henceforth use the terms <quote>Rotor</quote> and 
    <quote>SSCLI</quote> interchangeably.</para>
    
    <para>Rotor also contains source code for a C# compiler, implementing
    the ECMA-334<xref linkend="ecma-334"/> standard.</para>
       
  </sect1>
</chapter>
